Guide to the John D. Goheen Papers SC0267
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
John D. Goheen papers
1936-1977
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Goheen, John D.
SC0267
8 Linear Feet (15 boxes)
The papers pertain largely to East Asian studies at Stanford and in Japan and Taiwan, as well as Goheen's teaching and scholarly works. They include correspondence, memoranda, minutes, proposals, reports, papers, class materials, American Philosophical Association files, and photograph albums. Other subjects include an intercultural education project in the Palo Alto Unified School District, 1960-1962, and Goheen's appointment to Stanford.
Conditions Governing Access note
There are some personnel type materials in at least one file, possibly more. Needs review
Information about Access
This collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 48 hours in advance of intended use.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
John D. Goheen was a professor of philosophy at Stanford University from 1950 to 1972. Goheen, who earned his Ph.D. at Harvard, taught at Harvard and Queens College (New York) before coming to Stanford. He was instrumental in setting up the university's study centers in Japan and Taiwan in the 1960s; he was awarded the Order of the Sacred Treasure by the Japanese government for his contributions to U.S.-Japanese cultural and educational relations. He retired from teaching in 1972, but continued to be active on the Stanford campus, serving as the university Ombudsperson from 1974 to 1985.
Description of the Collection
The papers of John D. Goheen document his life as a student, teacher, and scholar, with special emphasis on his years at Stanford University and his role in developing overseas study centers in Japan and Taiwan. Included are correspondence, memoranda, minutes, proposals, reports, lecture notes, syllabi, manuscripts, and articles, largely dating from 1950 to 1977; correspondence files and photograph albums pertaining to the Seminar in American Studies at Tokyo and Stanford in Tokyo, 1951-1963; and Goheen's student notes and papers while at Harvard, 1931-1937. Also of note are correspondence files with the Ford Foundation and the Rockefeller Foundation concerning funding of programs, 1952-1963; materials pertaining to an intercultural education project in the Palo Alto Unified School District, 1960-62; and Goheen's correspondence files while an officer of the American Philosophical Association, 1968-1970.
Philosophy -- Study and teaching.; Albums.; Photoprints.; Intercultural education.; East Asia -- Study and teaching.; Stanford University. Department of Philosophy. Faculty; Palo Alto Unified School District.; Stanford University. Stanford Center for Chinese Studies in Taipei; Stanford University. East Asian Studies; American Philosophical Association.; Stanford University. Stanford Center for Japanese Studies; Goheen, John D.; Goheen, John D.
- Papers, Series 1
  - American Seminar in Japanese Studies, 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Center for East Asian Cultural Studies, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Committee on Comparative Thought (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Committee on Comparative Thought (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - East Asian Program Committee at Stanford, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - East Asian Research Committee at Stanford, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - East Asian Research Committee at Stanford, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - East Asian Studies at Stanford (Provost's Special Committee), 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Galvin, John A.T., letters to, 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - International Studies Committee (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Institute of International Education (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Interuniversity Program for Chinese Language Studies at Taipei, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Interuniversity Program for Chinese Language Studies at Taipei, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Japanese Studies Institute at Stanford (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Palo Alto Teachers' Program, 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1959-1963 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1952-1954 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Stanford correspondence, 1949-1951, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-1994-080
  - General Files, Subseries 1
    - American Philosophical Association 1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - American Philosophical Association 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - American Philosophical Association 1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - American Philosophical Association 1968-70 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - American Philosophical Association, Stanley Moore file, 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - American Studies Library (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - American Studies Program in Japan (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - American Studies Seminar, Miscellaneous Information, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Aristotle: Finished Essays (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - The Asia Foundation (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Augustine: Essays (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Carnap, Ina, letters to Nancy Goheen (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Chinese Thought (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, Miscellaneous, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Goheen: American Philosophy in the 20th Century (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Goheen: Aristotle (typed report) p 1-55 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Goheen: Aristotle (typed report) incomplete copy (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Goheen: Book Review, Rationalism in Greek Philosophy, by Boas, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Goheen: Book Review, A Study of Good by Nishada, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Goheen: Comment on Professor Kuklicks's paper, Berkeley, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Goheen: Comment on Professor Singer's "Cultural Values in India's Economic Development", 1958 Oct (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Goheen: "Concerning a Certain Tendency in French Ethical Thought" (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Goheen: "The Cost of Social Security" Chapter VI (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Goheen: The Development of Western Philosophy, 67 pages (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Goheen: The Development of Western Philosophy, 100 pages (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Goheen: Dewey and Miscellaneous Notes (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Goheen: "Faith and Reason" (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Goheen: "French Ethical Thought" (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Goheen: "Impressions of Change in Japan Since the War" (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Goheen "An Interpretation of Greek Philosophical Thought" (originals) (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Goheen "An Interpretation of Greek Philosophical Thought" 1-63 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Goheen "An Interpretation of Greek Philosophical Thought: Origins" p. 1-7 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Goheen "Intro. to Whitehead's Metaphysics" pp. 1-82 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Goheen "Intro. to Whitehead's Process and Reality final copy (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Goheen "Intro. to Whitehead's Process and Reality preliminary copy (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Goheen: Introductory lectures to Whitehead's Process and Reality (notebooks) (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Goheen: Introduction to Whitehead's Process and Reality (II), printed article in Japanese, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Goheen: Notes on James (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Goheen: "William James and His Philosophy of Pragmatism", 1950 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Goheen: "James and the Hellenistic Tradition" (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Goheen: "James and the Hellenistic Tradition" (mimeographed copy) (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Goheen: "William James and the Scientific Tradition (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Goheen "The Japanese Student" taped April 12, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Goheen: The meaning of "good" in Plato (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Goheen: The metaphysics of Dewey and Whitehead, ch. 1-7 (notebooks) (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Goheen: The metaphysics of Dewey and Whitehead, ch. 7-9, 5 (notebooks) (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Goheen: The metaphysics of Dewey and Whitehead, ch. 10-14 (notebooks) (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Goheen: The metaphysics of Dewey and Whitehead, ch. 15-16 (notebook) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Goheen: The metaphysics of Dewey and Whitehead: A Comparison Chapters I-IX (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Goheen: The metaphysics of Dewey and Whitehead: A Comparison Chapters X-XIII & Misc. Chapters (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Goheen: "New Trends in American Philosophy" (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Goheen: "Notes on Northrup's Meeting of East and West (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Goheen: Notes; Dewey, James, Darwin (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Goheen: Notes on Plato's Philebus (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Goheen: "Philosophy and this Crisis" (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Goheen: "Philosophy and this Crisis" (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Goheen: "Philosophy of Democracy" (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Goheen: Plato (typed report) (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Goheen: Plato, Essays (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Goheen: Plato, Essays (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Goheen: Plato, Philosophy of State (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Goheen: Preface for Ethics and Perinalology by John Goheen and George Cattermole (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Goheen: Presocratics (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Goheen: The problem of Philosophical Knowledge. (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Goheen: Rough Drafts (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Goheen: The Sophists (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Goheen: Sophists/ Socrates (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Goheen: Subjectivity and Objectivity in Lewis' Theory of Value (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Goheen: Notes on Talks (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Goheen: Teaching of Philosophy in the Introductory Course, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Goheen: Tendencies in American Philosophy (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Goheen: Various unpublished papers; some published reviews (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Goheen: What is Scientific Philosophy? (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Goldstein, Rob - Philosophy Papers (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Graduate Humanities exams (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Hiraga - foreign student, letter concerning, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - History 10, Western Civilization, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - History of Social Ideas; Bibliography (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Iino, Norimoto, correspondence, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - International House of Japan, correspondence, 1955-60 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Isenberg, Arnold, articles and papers, 1944-1966 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Isenberg, Arnold, articles and papers, vita, and one letter, 1949-1955 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Iwasaki, Takeo, correspondence, 1954-1963 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Japan Society, correspondence, 1958-1961 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Kishimoto, Hideo, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Komiya, Ryutare, correspondence, 1955-1959 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Lewis, C. I., correspondence with and about, 1952-1963 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Lewis, C. I., research correspondence, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Miner, Earl, correspondence, 1959-1962 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Miyamoto, Shoson, correspondence, 1955-1960 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Mothershead, John, correspondence, 1950-1964 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Murayama, Masao, letter, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Nagura, Dr. Eiji and Mioko, correspondence, 1952-1955 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Nakamura, Hajime, correspondence, 1953-1960 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Nakanishi, Hideo, correspondence, 1956 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Nakaya, Ken, correspondence, 1953-1960 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Nakayama, Shigeru, correspondence, 1954-1955 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Nishimura, Iwao (Fulbrights), correspondence, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Noda, Matao, correspondence and articles, 1951-1963 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Oche, Seizo, correspondence, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Ohfuti, Kaguo, correspondence, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Ohmori, Shozo, All Summer Seminar '56, correspondence and a paper, 1953-1956 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Okai, Nobushigi, correspondence, 1955-1960 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Peninsula Committee for Freedom in Education (flyer, newsletter, and notes), 1960, undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Philosophy 5, Lecture Notes (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Philosophy 5, Lecture notes on Extensional and Intensional Statements (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Philosophy 10, Introduction to Philosophical Analysis, syllabi, 1960-1967 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Philosophy 10, lecture notes, 1959-1960 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Philosophy 170 Theory of Value, Tokyo pp 1-100, 1956 summer (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Philosophy 170 Theory of Value, Tokyo pp 101-190, 1956 summer (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Philosophy and Literature, lecture notes, 1972-1973 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Philosophy of History, lecture notes (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Philosophy--American Philosophy, three lectures (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Philosophy--American Philosophy, lecture notes, UC Hayward, 1974 winter (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Philosophy--American Philosophy, lecture notes, 1967-1968 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Rockefeller Foundation, correspondence, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Shimizu, Hiroshi, correspondence, 1954-1955 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Stanford in Tokyo, Committee Minutes, 1957-1959 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Structured Liberal Education, lecture notes, 1976 fall/winter (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Structured Liberal Education, lecture notes, 1977 winter (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Takahashi, Tatsujiro of the Yoseido Gallery, correspondence, 1961-1962 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Tsurumi, Shunsuke, correspondence, 1952-1959 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - US National Commission for the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization (UNESCO), conference programs and notes, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Uyeda, Seizi, correspondence, 1951-1963 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Waseda University, correspondence re book collection for the Association for the Study of American Philosophy, 1954-1956 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Whitehead, Dewey MS Meeting, [Goheen's articles presumably used for that meeting], 1966 summer (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Wright, Arthur F. Papers and memoranda re East Asian thought (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Stanford in Tokyo Files, Subseries 2
    - Chenery-Shishido Research Project, correspondence, 1958-1960 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Endoh, Hiroshi, correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Festinger, Leon, correspondence, 1959-1960 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Gellhorn, Walter, correspondence, 1957-1958 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Hatano, Ichiro, correspondence, 1951-1962 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Kaji, Shinjo, correspondence, 1953-1955 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Kaji, Shinjo, correspondence, 1955-1963 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Kanamatsu, Kenryo, correspondence, 1953-1963 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Kawashima, Takeyoshi, correspondence, 1958-1960 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Konischi, Jinichi, correspondence, 1956-1958 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Kyogoku, Jun-ichi, correspondence and one article, 1958-1959 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Kuroda, Wataru, correspondence, 1961-1962 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Nakamura seminar, minutes and transcripts, 1951-1952 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Ogawa, Ichiro, correspondence, 1959-1960 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Okano, Yukihide, correspondence, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Pyle, Kenneth, correspondence, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Quine, Willard V., correspondence and one article, 1953-1959 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Taira, Koji, correspondence, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Shepard, Larry E., correspondence, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Shimizu, Tomohisa, correspondence, 1960-1961 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Shively, Donald, correspondence, 1959-1960 (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Smith, Thomas C., correspondence re summer conference, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - Spiller, Robert E., correspondence, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - Stanford-Tokyo Collaborative Studies Committee (agendas, memoranda, and correspondence), 1957-1960 (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - Stanford Chair in Japanese History and Civilization, correspondence re candidates, 1956-1960 (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - Tada, Michitaro, correspondence, 1955-1956 (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - Takahashi, Akiko, correspondence re sponsorship, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - Takayanagi, Shinichi, correspondence, 1957-1958 (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - Takeda, Hiromichi, correspondence and one article, 1951-1963 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Takeo, Jiichiro, correspondence, 1957-1960 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Toyoda, Takeshi, correspondence, 1958-1959 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Yamada, Chisaburoh, correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Yanaihara, Tadao, correspondence, 1957-1958 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Watanabe, Toshio, correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Yashiro, Yukio, correspondence, 1955-1959 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Yoshida, Teigo, correspondence, 1961 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Yoshimura, Masatoshi, correspondence and one photograph, 1960-1963 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Stanford in Tokyo, scrapbook, 1960-1961 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Student Papers, Subseries 3
    - Notebook, 1931-1936 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Notebook (C.I. Lewis on logic), no date (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Notebook (Socrates), no date (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Lecture notes, Whitehead at Harvard, 1936 Nov- 1937 May (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Essays on Whitehead, 1933-1935 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Essays on Whitehead, 1935-1937 (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Miscellaneous photographs (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Photocopies and typescripts of C. I. Lewis's papers (Box 11)
    - Photocopies and typescripts of C. I. Lewis's papers (Box 12)
  - Photograph Albums, Subseries 4
    - Seven photograph albums on the Seminar in American Studies at Tokyo, 1951-1956 (Box 13)
    - One photograph album on the opening of Stanford in Tokyo, includes photographs of J.E. Wallace Sterling, 1961 (Box 13)